The following content is provided under a
Creative Commons license. Your support will
help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high quality educational resources for
free. To make a donation or to view
additional materials from hundreds of MIT
courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare at ocw
.mit .edu. Well, OK. So first, important
things about the course, plans for the
course. And then today, I'm going to move
to the next section
of the notes,
section 2, or part 2, I should say. And
actually, I'll skip for the moment section
2 .1 and go to section 2 .2. And all of
chapter 2 will come to you probably today
or latest tomorrow. So that's where we're
going next. I'm following the notes pretty
carefully, except I'm going
to skip the section on tensors
until I learn more, basically. Yeah, yeah.
I could say a little about tensors. But
this flows naturally using the SVD. So it's
just a terribly important problem, least
squares. And of course, I know that you've
seen one or two ways to do least squares.
And really, the whole subject comes
together. Here, I want to say something
before I send out a plan for looking
ahead for the course as a whole.
So there's no final exam. And I don't
really see how to examine you, how to give
tests. I could, of course, create our tests
about the linear algebra part. But I don't
think it's not sort of the style of this
course. To expect you quickly to create a
proof or something in a class. So I think,
and especially looking at what we're headed
for and moving quite steadily in that
direction, is all the problems that this
linear algebra is aimed at, right up to and
including conjugate gradient descent and
deep learning. The big, the overwhelmingly
important and lively active research area.
I couldn't do better than to keep the
course going in that direction. So I think
what I would ask you to do is late in sort
of April, May, the regular homeworks I'll
discontinue at a certain point. And then
instead, I'll be asking and encouraging a
project. I don't know if that's the right
word to be using. In which you use what
we've done. And I'll send out a message on
Stellar listing like five or six areas. One
of them is the machine learning, deep
learning part. But there are all the other
parts that things we've learned are
learning how to do. How to find sparse
solutions, for example. Or something about
the pseudo -inverse. All kinds of things.
So that's my goal, is to give you something
to do which uses the material you've learned.
Not expecting a thesis, but it's a good
chance. So it will be more than just like
drag in some code for deep learning and
some data matrix and do it. But we'll talk
more as the time comes. So I just
thought I'd say, before sending out the
announcement, I
would say it's coming.
So a larger scale than single one week
homeworks would be here before. Any
thoughts about that? I haven't given you
details. So let me do that with a message
and then ask again. But I'm open to it. I
hope you've understood. I think you have.
That if you make suggestions either
directly to my email or on Piazza or
whatever, they get paid attention to. Shall
I just go forward with least squares? So
what's the least squares problem?
And what are these four ways?
So let me speak about the pseudo -inverse
first. OK. The pseudo -inverse of a matrix.
All right. Good.
So we have a matrix A, m by n. And the
pseudo -inverse I'm going to call A plus.
And it naturally is going to be n by m. I'm
going to multiply those together. And I'm
going to get as near to the identity as
I can. That's the idea, of course, of the
pseudo -inverse. The word pseudo is
in there, so no one's deceived. It's not an
actual inverse. Oh, if the matrix is square
and has an inverse, of course, then if A
inverse exists,
which requires a, everybody remembers, it
requires the matrix to be square, because I
mean inverse on both sides. And it requires
rank n, full rank. Then the inverse will
exist. You can check it. Matlab would check
it by computing the pivots in elimination
and finding n pivots. So if A inverse
exists, which means A times A inverse and A
inverse times A both give I,
then A plus is A inverse, of course.
The pseudo -inverse is the inverse when
there is one. But I'm thinking about cases
where either the matrix is rectangular,
or it has zero eigenvalues. It could be
square, but has a null space other than
just the zero vector. In other words, the
columns are dependent. What can we do
then about inverting it? We can't literally
invert it. If A has a null space, then
when I multiply by a vector x in that null
space, Ax will be 0. And when I multiply by
A inverse, still 0. That can't change the
0. So if there is an x in the null space,
then this can't happen. But so we just do
the best we can. And that's what the pseudo
-inverse is. And so let me draw a picture
of the picture you
know of the row space
and the null space. And it's there. You
see, there is a null space. And over here,
I have the column space and
the null space of A transpose.
So this is the row space, of course. That's
the column space of A transpose. And there
is the column space of A. So which part of
that picture is invertible, and which part
of the picture is hopeless? The top part is
invertible. This is the R dimensional row
space, R dimensional column space. A takes
a vector in here, zaps it into every. Oh,
you always end up in the column space.
Here, I take a vector in the row space, say
x. And it gets mapped to Ax. And between
those two spaces, A is entirely invertible.
And you get separate vectors here, go to
separate vectors in the column space. And
the inverse just brings it back. So we know
what the pseudo -inverse should do. A will
go that way. And A plus, the pseudo
-inverse, will be just, it will give us, on
the top half of the picture, it'll give us
A plus. We'll take Ax back to x in the top
half. Now, what about here? That's where
we have trouble. We don't have, that's what
spoils our inverse. If there is a null
space vector, then it goes where? When you
multiply by A, this guy in
the null space goes to 0.
Transpose, because A, sorry, yeah, what
should the pseudo -inverse do? I said, what
should the inverse do? The inverse is
helpless. But we have to define A plus.
I've said what it should do on that
guy, on the column space. It should take
everything in the column space back where
it came from. But what should it do on this
orthogonal space where, yeah, just tell me.
What do you think? GILBERT STRANGER I have
some vector here that's, let's call it v r
plus 1. That would be like the, so here I
have a basis of a nice basis for the column
space. There's v's. I would use v's for
the ones that come up in the SVD. They're
orthogonal, and they come from orthogonal
u's. So that top half is great. What shall
I do with this stuff? I'm going to send
that back by A plus. And where am I going?
What am I going to do with it? Send it to?
Nowhere else could it go. 0 is the right
answer. All this stuff goes back to 0.
I'm looking for a linear operator, a
matrix. And I have to think of, once I've
decided what to do with all those, and what
to do with all these, then I know what to
do with any combination. So I've got it.
I've got it. So the idea will be, this is
true for x in the row space.
For x in the row space,
if x is in the row space, Ax is in the
column space, and A inverse just brings it
back as it should.
Matrix A, what happens to my picture?
What is this picture looking like if A is
actually a 6 by 6 invertible matrix? In
that case, what's in my picture, and what
is not in my picture?
Null space. GILBERT STRANG All this null
space stuff isn't there. And null space is
just the 0 vector.
But all that I don't have to worry
about. But in general, I do have to say.
A plus on the, what
am I calling this?
It's the null space of A transpose,
or whatever on vr plus 1 to vn.
All those vectors, the guys that are not
orthogonal to the column space, then we
have to say, what does A plus do to them?
And the answer is, it takes them all to 0.
So there is a picture using what I call
the big picture of linear algebra, the four
spaces. You see what A plus should do. Now,
I need a little formula for it. I've got
the plan for what it should be, and it's
sort of the natural thing. So A plus A is,
you could say, it's a projection matrix.
It's not the identity matrix, because if x
is in the null space, A plus A will take
it to 0. So it's a projection. A plus A is
the identity on the top half and 0 on the
bottom half. That's really what the matrix
is. And now, I want a simple formula for
it. And I guess my message here is that if
we're looking for a nice expression, start
with the SVD, because the SVD works for any
matrix. And it writes it as an orthogonal
matrix times a diagonal matrix times an
orthogonal matrix. And now, I want to
invert it. Well, suppose A had an inverse.
What would that be?
This is if invertible.
What would be the SVD of A inverse? What
would be the singular value decomposition
if this is good? So when is this going to
be good? What would I have to know about
that matrix sigma, that diagonal matrix in
the middle, if this is truly an invertible matrix?
Well, no. What's its name? Those are not
eigenvalues. Well, they're eigenvalues of A
transpose A. But they're singular values.
Singular value, that's fine. So that's the
singular value matrix. And what would
be the situation if A had an inverse?
There would be no 0s. All the singular
values would be sitting there, sigma 1 to
sigma n. What would be the shape of this
sigma matrix? If I have an inverse, then
it's got to be square n by n. So what's the
shape of the sigma guy? Also square n by
n. So the invertible case would be, and
I'm going to erase this in a minute, the
invertible case would be when sigma is just
that. That would be the invertible case.
So let's see. Finish this formula. What
would be the SVD of A inverse? So I'm given
the SVD of A. I'm given the u and the
sigmas, cool, and the V transpose. What's
the inverse of that? Yeah, I'm just really
asking you, what's the inverse of that
product of three matrices?
What comes first here? V. The inverse
of V transpose is V. That's because V is a
orthogonal matrix. The inverse of sigma,
I just won over it. It's just the sigma
inverse. It's obvious what that means. And
the inverse of u would go here, and that
is? U transpose. U transpose, great. OK,
so this is if invertible. If invertible, we
know what the SVD of A inverse
is. It just takes the Vs back to the Us.
Or the Us back to the Vs, whichever. OK,
OK. Now we've got to do it if we're going
to allow, if we're going to get beyond this
limit situation, allow the matrix sigma to
be rectangular. Then let me just show you
the idea here. So now I'm going to say, now
sigma, in general, it's rectangular. It's
got r non -zeros on the diagonal, but then
it quits. So it's got a bunch of zeros that
make it not invertible. But let's do our
best and pseudo invert it. OK, so now
help me get started on a formula for using.
This A plus, which I described up there in
terms of the subspaces. Now I'm going to
describe A plus in terms of u, sigma, and V
in the SVD guys. OK, so what shall I start
with here? Well, let me give a hint.
That was a great start. My V is still an
orthogonal matrix. V transpose is still an
orthogonal matrix. I'll invert it. At the
end, the u was no problem. All the problems
are in sigma. In sigma, remember, sigma,
so it's rectangular. Maybe I'll make it
like wide for too wide. And maybe I'll only
give it two non -zeros and then all
the rest. So the rank of my matrix A is 2.
m and n are bigger than 2. It's just got
two independent columns, and then it's just
sort of totally singular. OK, so my
question is, what am I going to put there?
And I've described it one way, but now I'm
going to describe it another way. Well, let
me just say, what I'll put there is the
pseudo inverse of sigma. I can't put sigma
inverse using that symbol, because there
is no such thing. With this, I can't invert
it. So that's the best I can do. So I'm
almost done. But to finish, I have to tell
you, what is this thing? So sigma plus, I'm
now going to tell you sigma plus. And then
that's what should sit there in the middle.
So if sigma is this diagonal matrix which
quits after two sigmas, what should sigma
plus be? Well, first of all, it should be
rectangular the other way. If this was m by
n column, n columns and m rows, now I want
to have n rows and m columns. And
yeah, here's the question. What's the best
inverse you could come
up with for that sigma?
Is it of 18065? If somebody asks you,
do your best to invert that matrix. I think
we'd all agree it is. Yeah? 1 over sigma.
GILBERT STRANG. 1 over the sigma 1 would
come there. And 1 over sigma 2, the non
-zeros. And then? Zeros. Just the way up
there. When we didn't know what to do, when
there was nothing good to do, 0 was the
right answer. So this is all zeros. Of
course, it's rectangular the other way. But
do you see that if I multiply sigma
plus times sigma, if I multiply the pseudo
-inverse times the matrix, what
do I get if I multiply that by that?
What does that multiplication produce? Can
you describe the? Well, when you tell me
what it looks like, I'll write it down. So
what is sigma plus times sigma? If sigma is
a diagonal, sigma plus is a diagonal. And
they both quit after two guys. What do I have?
1. GILBERT STRANG. Because sigma 1 times 1
over sigma 1 is a 1. And the other next guy
is? A 1. And the rest are? All zeros.
That's right. It's the best I could do. The
rank was only 2. So I couldn't get
anywhere. So that tells you what sigma plus is.
OK. So I described the pseudo -inverse then
with a picture of spaces and then with a
formula of matrices. And now I want to use
it in least squares. So now I'm going to
say, what is the least squares problem? And
the first way to solve it will be to let,
to involve, A plus will give the solution.
OK. So what is the least squares problem?
Let me put it here.
OK. The least squares problem is
simply you have an equation Ax equal b.
But A is not invertible. So you can't solve
it. Of course, for which, yeah, you could
find, you could solve it for certain b's.
If b is in the column space of A, then just
by the meaning of column space, this has
a solution. The vectors in the column space
are the guys that you can get. But the
vectors in the orthogonal space, you cannot
get, or all the rest of the vectors you
cannot get. So suppose this is like so, but
always A is m by n rank r.
And then we get A inverse when m equals
n equals r. That's the invertible case. OK.
What do we do with a system of equations?
When we can't solve it. This is probably
the main application in 18 .06. So you've
seen this problem before. What do we do if
Ax equal b has no solution? Typically, b
would be a vector of measurements, like
we're tracking a satellite. And
we get some measurements.
And often, we get too many measurements.
And of course, there's a little noise in
them. And a little noise means that we
can't solve the equations. That maybe, the
case everybody knows is where this equation
is like expressing a straight line going
through the data points. So the famous
example of these squares is fit a straight
line. A straight line
to the b's. To b1, b2. We've got m
measurements. We've got m measurements. The
physics or the mechanics of the problem is
pretty well linear. But of course, there's
noise. And the straight line only has two
degrees of freedom. So we're going to have
only two columns in our matrix. A will
be only two columns with many rows.
Highly rectangular. So fit a straight line.
Let me call that line Cx plus d. Say this
is the x direction. This is the b's
direction. And we've got a whole bunch of
data points. And
they're not on a line.
Suppose those did lie on a line. What would
that tell me about Ax equal b? I haven't
said everything I need to. But maybe
the insight is what I'm after here. If my
points are right on a line, so there is a
straight line through them. The unknowns
here. So Ax. The unknowns here are C and D. And
the right hand side is all my measurements. OK.
Suppose, without my drawing a picture,
suppose these points are on a line. Here is
the different x's, the measurement
times. Here is the different measurements.
But if they're on a line, what does that
tell me about my linear system Ax equal b?
It has a solution. Being on a line means
everything's perfect. There is a solution.
But will there usually be a solution?
Certainly not. If I have only two
parameters, two
unknowns, two columns here,
the rank is going to be 2. And
here I'm trying to hit any noisy set of
measurements. So of course, in general, the
picture will look like that. And I'm going
to look for the best C
and D. So I'll call it Cx
plus D. Yeah. Right. Sorry. That's my line.
So those are my equations. So oh, sorry. I
often write it C plus Dx. Do you mind if
I put the constant term first in the highly
difficult equation
here for a straight line?
So let me tell you what I'm. So these are
the points where you have a measurement,
x1, x2 up to xm. And these are the actual
measurements, b1 up to bm, let's say. And
the equations are, I just want to set up
the matrix here. I just want to set up the
matrix. So I want C to get multiplied
by 1's every time. And I want D to get
multiplied by these x's, x1, x2, x3, xm,
the measurement places. And those are the
measurements. Anyway.
The problem is this has no solution. And
so what do I do when there's no solution?
Well, I'll do what Gauss did. He was a good
mathematician, so I'll follow his advice.
I won't do it all semester, as you know.
But Gauss's advice was minimize. I'll blame
it on Gauss. The distance between Ax
and b squared, the L2 norm squared,
which is just Ax minus b transpose Ax minus
b. It's a quadratic. And minimizing it
gives me a system of linear equations. So
in the end, they will have a solution. So
that's the whole point of these squares.
We have an unsolvable problem, no solution.
We follow Gauss's advice to get the best
we can. And that does produce an answer. So
this is, if I multiply this out, is x
transpose A transpose Ax. That comes from
the square term. And I have probably these
actually will probably get two of those and
then a constant term that has derivative
0 so it doesn't enter. So this is what I'm
minimizing. This is the loss function.
And it leads to, let's just jump to the key
here. What equation do I get when I look
for what equation is solved by the best x?
The best x. The best x solves the famous. So this
is regression in statistics, linear regression.
It's one of the main computations
in statistics, not, of course, just for
straight line fits, but for any system Ax
equal b. That will lead to, this minimum
will lead to a system of equations that I'm
going to put a box around because it's so
fundamental. And are you willing to tell
me what that equation is? Yes, thanks. A
transpose A. A transpose A is going to come
from there. You see it. Times the best x equals.
As x transpose A transpose B. So it's
x transpose against A transpose B. It's
linear. So when I take the derivative, it's
that constant. That's pretty fast. 18 .06
would patiently derive that. But here, let
me give you the picture that goes with it.
The geometry. So
we have the problem.
No solution. We have Gauss's best answer.
Minimize the 2 norm of the error. We have
the conclusion, the matrix that we get in.
And now I want to draw a picture that goes
with it. OK. So
here is a picture.
Now I've got to put b in the picture. So
where does this vector b? So I'm trying to
solve Ax equal b, but failing. So if I draw
b in this picture, how do I draw b? Where
do I put it? Shall I put it in the column
space? No. The whole point is it's not in
the column space. It's not an
Ax. Out there somewhere. B. OK.
And then what's the geometry that goes with
these squares and the normal equations and
Gauss's suggestion to minimize the error?
Where will Ax be? The best Ax that I can
do. Where will? So what Gauss has produced
is an A. He can't find an x. He'll do his
best he can. And we're calling that guy x
hat. And this is the algebra to find x hat.
And now where is the picture here? Where
is this vector Ax hat, which is the best Ax
we can get? So it has to be in the column
space, because it's A times something. And
where is it in the column
space? It's the projection.
That's Ax hat. And here is the error, which
you couldn't do anything about. B minus Ax
hat. Yeah. So it's
the projection. Right.
Justifying the so we're in the second
approach to least squares. Solve the normal
equations. Solve the normal equations.
Yeah. That would be the second approach to
least squares. And most examples, if
they're not very big or very difficult, you
just create a matrix A transpose A. And you
call MATLAB and solve that linear system.
You create the matrix. You create
the right -hand side. And you solve it.
So that's the ordinary run -of -the
-mill least squares problem. Just do it.
So that's method
two. Just do it.
What's method three?
Problem here. But now I'm thinking
it may be a little more difficult.
This matrix A transpose A might be nearly
singular. Gauss is assuming that, yeah.
Yeah. When did this work? When did this
work? And it will continue to work in the
next three. This works.
This is good if assuming
A has independent columns.
Yeah. Better just make clear. I'm
claiming that when A has in. So what's the
reasoning? Independent columns, but maybe
not enough columns, like here. It's only
got two columns. It's obviously not going
to be able to match any right -hand side.
But it's got independent columns. When A
has independent columns, then what can I
say about this matrix?
It's invertible. Gauss's plan works. If A
has independent columns, then this would be
a linear algebra. Step. Then this will be
invertible. You see the importance of that
step. If A has independent columns, that
means it has no null space. Only x equals 0
is in the null space. Two independent
columns, but only two. So not enough to
solve systems, but independent. Then you're
OK. This matrix is invertible. You can do
what Gauss tells you.
We're prepared now.
We have to think, OK.
So what do I really want to do? I want to
connect this Gauss's solution to the pseudo
-inverse, because I'm claiming they both
give the same result. The pseudo -inverse,
yeah. The pseudo
-inverse will apply.
But we have something. This A is not
invertible. Just keep remembering this
matrix. It's not invertible, but it has got
independent columns. What am I saying
there? Just going
back to the picture.
If A has a matrix with independent columns,
what space disappears in this picture?
The null space goes away. So the picture is
simpler. But it's still the null space of
A transpose. This is still pretty big,
because I only had two columns and a whole
lot of rows. And that's going to be
reflected here. So what am I trying to say?
I'm trying to say that this answer is the
same as the pseudo -inverse answer. We
could possibly even check that
point. Let me write it down first.
I claim
that the answer A plus B is the same as
the answer coming from here, A transpose A
inverse A transpose B, when I guess
the null space is 0, the rank is all of n,
whatever you like to say. I believe that
method 1, this two -identification in one
quick formula. So remember that this was V
sigma plus U transpose, right? That's what
A transpose was. That
this should agree with this.
I believe those are the same when the null
space isn't in the picture. So the fact
that the null space is just the 0 vector
means that this inverse does exist. So this
inverse exists, but A A
transpose is not invertible,
right? No inverse.
Because A A transpose would be coming with
A transpose. All this is a null space of A
transpose. A transpose
is not invertible.
But A transpose A is invertible.
How would you check that?
You see what I'm? It's taken pretty
much the whole hour to get a picture of the
geometry of the pseudo -inverse.
So this is the pseudo -inverse.
And this is that matrix there. It's really
doing its best to be the inverse. In fact,
everybody here is just doing their best to
be the inverse. Now, how well is this? How
close is that to being the inverse? Can I
just ask you about that, and then I'll make
this connection, and then we're out of time.
How close is that to being the inverse of A?
Suppose I multiply that by A.
What do I get? So just notice.
If I multiply that by A, what
do I get? I get, yeah? I get I.
Terrific.
But don't be deceived to thinking that this
is the inverse of A. It worked on the left
side, but it's not going to be good on the right
-hand side. So if I multiply A by this guy in
that direction, I'll get as close to the
identity as I can come, but I won't get the
identity that way. So this
is just a little box to say.
So what's the point of making?
This is a pseudo -inverse, whatever.
Whatever these spaces. The rank could be
tiny, just 1. This works when the rank is
n. I needed independent columns. So when
the rank is n, so this is rank equal n.
That Gauss worked. Then I can get a one
-sided inverse, but it's not a two -sided
inverse. I can't do that. Look, my matrix
there. I could find a one -sided inverse to
get the 2 by 2 identity, but I could never
multiply that by some matrix and get the n
by n identity out of those two pathetic columns.
Maybe you feel like just checking this. Just
takes patience. What do I mean by checking it?
I mean,
stick in the SVD. Just put in the SVD and
cancel like crazy. And I think that'll pop
out. Do you believe me? Because it's
going to be a little painful. 3, u sigma v
transpose, all transposed, and then
something there and something there. I've
got nine matrices multiplying away. But
it's going to, like all sorts of things,
will produce the identity. And in the end,
that's what I'll have. Yeah. So this is the
one -sided true inverse, where the SVD,
this formula is prepared to have neither
side invertible. It's still, we know what
sigma plus means. Anyway, so under the
assumption of independent columns, Gauss works
and gives the same answer as the pseudo -inverse.
OK, three minutes. That's hardly time. But
this being MIT, I feel I should use it. Oh
my god, number three.
So what's number three about? Number three
has the same requirement as number two, the
same requirement of no null space. But
it says, if I could get orthogonal columns
first, then this problem would be easy. So
everybody knows that Gram -Schmidt is a
way, a boring way, to get from these two
columns to get two orthogonal columns.
Actually, the whole idea of Gram -Schmidt
is already there for 2 by 2. So I have two
minutes, and we can do it. Let's do Gram
-Schmidt on these two columns. Column A.
Column I don't want to use u and v.
Column y and z. OK. Suppose I want to
orthogonalize those guys. What's the Gram
-Schmidt idea? I take y. It's perfectly
good. No problem with y. There is
the y vector, all 1s. Then this guy is not
orthogonal, probably, to that. It'll go
off in this direction. Angle that's not 90
degrees. So what do I do? I want to get
orthogonal vectors. I'm OK with this first
guy. But the second guy isn't orthogonal
to the first. So what do I do? In this
picture, how do I come up
with a vector orthogonal to y?
Project. I could take this z, and I take
its projection. So z has a little piece.
That z vector has a big piece already in
the direction of y, which I don't want, and
a piece orthogonal to it. That's my other
piece. That's my other piece. So here's y,
and here's the, this is, that is z minus a
projection, let me just say. Whatever. I
don't know if I even drew that picture
right. Probably I didn't. Anyway, whatever.
The Gram -Schmidt idea is just
orthogonalize in the natural way. I'll come
back to that at the beginning of next
time and say a word about the fourth way.
So this least squares is not deep learning.
It's what people did a century ago and
continue to do for good reason. OK. And
I'll send out that announcement about the
class. And you know the homework, and you
know the new due date is Friday. Good. Thank you.